<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <title>Scarab</title>

  <subtitle>The Definitive Guide</subtitle>

  <bookinfo>
    <author>
      <firstname>Daniel</firstname>

      <surname>Patterson</surname>
    </author>

    <copyright>
      <year>2003</year>
    </copyright>
  </bookinfo>

  <preface>
    <title>Preface</title>

    <para></para>

    <sect1>
      <title>Audience</title>

      <para>This book is targette</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>How This Book is Organised</title>

      <para></para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Typographic Conventions</title>

      <para></para>
    </sect1>
  </preface>

  <glossary>
    <glossdiv>
      <title></title>

      <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Issue Type</glossterm>

        <glosssee>A definition of a type of issue, which is essentially a
        collection of attributes. Common issue types are &#34;Bug&#34; or
        &#34;Enhancement&#34;.</glosssee>
      </glossentry>

      <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Issue</glossterm>

        <glosssee>An instance of an issue type inside a module. An issue is
        something that a user has entered into the system.</glosssee>
      </glossentry>

      <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Attribute</glossterm>

        <glosssee>An attribute is an item of data to be stored about an issue.
        Attributes represent things like names, dates, status&#39;,
        descriptions, etc.</glosssee>
      </glossentry>

      <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Module</glossterm>

        <glosssee>Modules are where issues are created. Modules let you group
        issues together (e.g. per-project, or per-customer).</glosssee>
      </glossentry>
    </glossdiv>
  </glossary>

  <chapter>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <sect1>
      <title>What is Scarab?</title>

      <para>Scarab is a customisable issue tracking system. It allows you to
      create issue types that suite your needs, then collect and track data on
      those issue types.</para>

      <para>It is web based and written in Java. It stores issue information
      in a database, MySQL being the primary platform, but it is also rumoured
      to work on Oracle, PostgreSQL and DB2. It runs as a J2EE web application
      (WAR), and by default, comes bundled with the Tomcat servlet container.
      This, along with a MySQL database is all you need to get up and running.</para>

      <sect2>
        <title>How Scarab Differs from other issue tracking systems</title>

        <para>Scarab is extremely customisable. It contains no hard-coded
        workflow (e.g. Bugs move from Open to Closed) and no hard-coded issue
        type definitions. You have complete freedom to define your issues the
        way you want them. The downside of this is a bit more start-up effort,
        but you get something that more closely fits your needs.</para>

        <para>Most other issue-trackers (Bugzilla, Issuezilla, SourgeForge,
        Gnats) contain issue-processing logic as part of the application. This
        means you&#39;re often stuck in the workflow defined by that system.
        Scarab does not limit you in this way and gives you a much bigger gun
        to blow your foot off with.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Scarab&#39;s History</title>

      <para>TODO</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Scarab&#39;s Features</title>

      <para>TODO</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Basic Concepts</title>

    <para>In this section, we&#39;ll examine the basic concepts that drive
    Scarab so that when you see the user interface, you&#39;ll understand what
    is being represented on screen.</para>

    <sect1>
      <title>The Anatomy of an Issue</title>

      <para>Scarab is a system for storing issues. Because everyone has their
      own idea about what kind of issue data they should be capturing, Scarab
      lets you define your own structure.</para>

      <sect2>
        <title>Issue Types</title>

        <para>An issue type is a description of the structure of a set of
        issues. An issue type might be a Bug, a Defect, a Work Order, a Help
        Request, etc. It is up to you to define what your issue types are.
        Issue types themselves are not issues, they simply describe what
        information can be captured for that type.</para>

        <para>There are two kinds of issue types. Global and module. Global
        issue types themselves only act as a template for creating issue-types
        on a per-module basis (for a description of modules, see lower down).
        Module issue-types are what define the information that is captured
        for each issue-type in each module.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Attributes</title>

        <para>Attributes are the pieces of information that you bundle
        together in your issue type definitions. An attribute is an atomic
        piece of information, like &#34;name&#34; or &#34;description&#34; or
        &#34;Operating System&#34;.</para>

        <para>Attributes are created globally in Scarab. Where possible,
        it&#39;s a good idea to re-use attributes between issue-types. This
        will allow you, should you want to, to produce reports for issues
        across different modules that share common attributes.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Issues</title>

        <para>An issue is an &#34;instance&#34; of an issue type. An issue is
        what you enter data for. Issues are given a unique identifier. In
        addition to the attributes you define in the issue type definition, an
        issue also has the following information associated with it:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Attachments</para>

            <para>You can attach (multiple) files to issues. This is useful
            for adding extra information related to an issue alongside it
            (i.e. a logfile that was taken when a bug was found)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Comments</para>

            <para>Arbitary comments can be added to issues. This is where
            general commentary about the issue is stored (i.e. discussion
            about the issue). Comments are appended as they are added, as
            opposed to issue attributes, which contain only a single value.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Dependencies</para>

            <para>Dependencies can be used to describe relationships between
            issues. Dependencies can be:</para>

            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Blocking</para>

                <para>This means that the related issue prevents some kind of
                further action on the issue you are looking at. This
                relationship is descriptive, it doesn&#39;t actually stop you
                doing anything in Scarab, it simply tells you something about
                the relationship between the issues.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Non-blocking</para>

                <para>This means that the related issue doesn&#39;t prevent
                things happening to the issue you are looking at.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Duplicate</para>

                <para>This means that the related issue is the same as the one
                you are looking at.</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>URLs</para>

            <para>This is a place to store URL&#39;s that provide additional
            information for the issue (this may be a link to a page that
            demonstrates a bug, if the product you&#39;re capturing issues for
            is a website for example).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Personnel</para>

            <para>You can create associations between an issue and users in
            the system. The &#34;name&#34; of the association is configured by
            you as part of the issue type, and will usually look something
            like &#34;assigned to&#34;, or &#34;owned by&#34; or
            &#34;interested in&#34;. Again, these associations are only
            informational, and don&#39;t actually infer any different
            functionality in Scarab based on their value or name (i.e.
            it&#39;s up to you to interpret what the information means).</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Issue modification audit trail</title>

        <para>All changes to everything on an issue is tracked in the issues
        audit trail. For changes to issue attributes, you almost always
        (comments are the exceptions) have to supply a reason for your change.
        All changes are logged, along with the reason for each change.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Modules</title>

      <para></para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Installation</title>

    <para>In this section, we&#39;ll outline the basic installation process.
    Because Scarab is written as a J2EE Web Application, this means that you
    can deploy it in a few different ways. Scarab comes bundled with a copy of
    Apache Tomcat, a servlet container, that you can use to run Scarab
    out-of-the-box. Take a look at the later section &#34;Alternative ways of
    running&#34; for some clues on how to run Scarab in a not out-of-the-box
    way.</para>

    <sect1>
      <title>Building the code</title>

      <para></para>

      <sect2>
        <title>Prerequisites</title>

        <para>Ant</para>

        <para>Java 1.3.1 or higher</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Getting the code</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Configuring the build</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Build it!</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Creating the database</title>

      <para></para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Running Scarab</title>

      <para></para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Alternative ways of running</title>

      <para></para>

      <sect2>
        <title>Deploying as a J2EE WAR</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Running under other Servlet containers</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Platform Specific Notes</title>

      <para></para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Using Scarab</title>

    <para>This section will outline how you use Scarab in a day to day way.
    We&#39;ll cover all the common things you do, as well as some of the
    not-so-common ones.</para>

    <para>In general, the majority of the tasks that you will perform inside
    Scarab will be related to the creation and update of issues. However,
    there are a few other things you can do and sometimes need to do before
    other portions of the system will do anything useful.</para>

    <para>Lets begin.</para>

    <sect1>
      <title>Registering for an Account</title>

      <para></para>

      <sect2>
        <title>Creating your account</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Getting access to modules</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Issues</title>

      <para>This section will outline the majority of the operations
      you&#39;ll perform when inside Scarab.</para>

      <sect2>
        <title>Creating a new Issue</title>

        <para>1. Select the appropriate module</para>

        <para>2. Choose the issue type you want to create</para>

        <para>3. Fill out the details for the issue</para>

        <para>4. If present, identify duplicates</para>

        <para>5. Complete!</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Modfying an Issue</title>

        <para>1. Find the issue you want to modify (either by query, or by
        entering the number in the search box)</para>

        <sect3>
          <title>Changing attribute data</title>

          <para></para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>Modifying Personnel information</title>

          <para></para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>Adding comments</title>

          <para></para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>Adding attachments and URLs</title>

          <para></para>
        </sect3>

        <sect3>
          <title>Setting up dependencies between issues</title>

          <para></para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Viewing an issues history</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Deleting issues (and why you can&#39;t)</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Moving/copying issues</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Creating and Using Templates</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Queries</title>

      <para></para>

      <sect2>
        <title>Module Queries</title>

        <para>For each issue-type in your module,</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Cross-module Queries</title>

        <para>If you&#39;ve defined the same issue-type (or even remotely
        similar issue types that share attributes) in multiple modules, you
        can create queries that span many modules. This is useful for finding
        out things across many projects (i.e. show me all open issues in
        modules X, Y and Z).</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Pre-defined queries</title>

        <para>There are a couple of pre-defined queries. The &#34;My
        Issues&#34; query will show you all issues that have you assigned in
        some way as a &#34;personnel attribute&#34;.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Saving queries</title>

        <para>Queries can be saved, making it easy to create queries that do
        things like &#34;show me all bugs in the &#34;open&#34; state&#34;, or
        &#34;show me all bugs that were opened this week&#34;.</para>

        <sect3>
          <title>Personal vs. Module wide</title>

          <para>Personal queries are only visible to you, module-wide queries
          are visible to all people in that module and require approval to
          create (although, you may have that permission yourself).</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Customising your query results</title>

        <para>Adding/removing attributes from view, sorting, exporting to XLS,
        CSV.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Reports</title>

      <para></para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Administration</title>

    <para></para>

    <sect1>
      <title>Configuration</title>

      <para></para>

      <sect2>
        <title>Structure and Layout</title>

        <para>**Best practises</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Re-use principals</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Creating Modules</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Creating Attributes and Issue Types</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Adding Issue Types to Modules</title>

        <para></para>

        <sect3>
          <title>Customising Issue Types</title>

          <para></para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>User Management</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Roles and Permissions</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Approvals</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Email configuration</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Backups</title>

      <para>Outline what needs to be backed up</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Imports and Exports</title>

      <para></para>

      <sect2>
        <title>Settings</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
        <title>Issue Data</title>

        <para></para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Search Indexes</title>

      <para></para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Customisation</title>

    <para>In this section, we&#39;ll examine the various options you&#39;ve
    got for customising Scarab to fit in your environment. This section will
    not discuss how to customise issue types, see the Administration chapter
    for that.</para>

    <sect1>
      <title>Customising templates</title>

      <para>Email templates, web templates, how to go about upgrading without
      breaking</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Customising the authentication database</title>

      <para></para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Workflow customisation</title>

      <para></para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Development</title>

    <para></para>

    <sect1>
      <title>How to Contribute</title>

      <para>Lurk on the mailing lists</para>

      <para>Get code, hack</para>

      <para>Submit patches</para>

      <para>Get CVS access</para>

      <para>(refer to existing how to contribute doc)</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Resources</title>

      <para>Where to get the code, what libs are used and where they&#39;re
      from, what technologies/standards are adhered to. Mailing lists,
      websites. Fill this in properly.</para>

      <para>Reference the FAQ.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Architecture and Design</title>

      <para>Data model: How data is stored (torque), issues, attributes,
      modules, activities</para>

      <para>User interface: layouts, templates</para>

      <para>Business logic: ....</para>
    </sect1>
  </chapter>

  <appendix>
    <title>Troubleshooting</title>

    <para>Include some items from the FAQ here (particularly those about
    database errors).</para>
  </appendix>
</book>