<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
<properties>
<title>Scarab - Hypersonic</title>
<author email="epugh@OpensourceConnections.com">Eric Pugh</author>
<author email="Jason.Gillam NO SPAM vignette.com">Gillam, Jason</author>
</properties> 
<body>

<section name="Hypersonic">
<p>
1 - set property: scarab.database.type=hypersonic (note - this will generate
the scripts but the current ant script won't automatically install the
database schema for a hypersonic db.  You'll have to manually load them.)
</p>


<p>
2 - set other DB properties to point to your hypersonic DB.  You need to run in server mode
</p>

<p>
4 - Torque has a bug when generating hypersonic scripts.  The only script in
scarab which exposes the problem is the scarab.sql file.  You will have to
manually go in there and look for an extra comma at the end of each table
column definition in the CREATE statements.  Some of them have the extra
comma (which needs to be deleted), and others are okay.
</p>



<p>
6 - Use one of the hypersonic tools (DatabaseManager works well) to open and
execute each of the .sql scripts in the same order that they appear in the
create-mysql-database.bat/.sh file.
</p>

<p>
---
Outstanding Issues:
</p>

<p>
Just this one.  The scarab web application appears to be working, including
the e-mail registration part.  I'm stuck at a spot where I don't seem to be
authorized to do anything (not even the admin account is).  So I can't add
modules or even see any issues in the sample application.  Whether this is a
problem with Scarab or a problem with hypersonic has yet to be determined.
Nothing showed up in the application server logs.
</p>

<p>
If anyone figures this out, please post a response.  Hypersonic makes an
excellent platform for small deployments because it's opensource and you
don't have to run a full database in a separate process (i.e. standalone
"file" mode).
</p>



<h4>Basic instructions</h4>
Torque generates the sql properly except for a couple modifications.  After run ant create-db go
into /target/scarab/web-inf/sql/hypersonic and do these changes:
<ol>
<li> Change all # to --</li>

<li> Change all drops from "drop table if exists TURBINE_USER_GROUP_ROLE;" to
"drop table TURBINE_USER_GROUP_ROLE is exists"</li>

<li>change mediumblob to object</li>

<li> change mediumtext to varchar</li>
</ol>

Then rerun the ant create-db and it'll work.
</section>
</body>
</document>