<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
<properties>
<title>Scarab - MSSQL</title>
<author email="epugh@OpensourceConnections.com">Eric Pugh</author>
</properties>

<body>

  <section name="Database Details">
    <p>
    Scarab has been developed with database independence in mind, however
    our primary goal is to make Scarab work with MySQL. Therefore, our
    support for other RDBM's is largely untested. We are relying on the user
    community in order to help us test and develop further support for other
    databases. This document outlines the steps that we think are required
    to get Scarab working with MSSQL. <a
    href="mailto:dev@scarab.tigris.org">Community feedback</a> on this
    document will help improve things for others.
    </p>
    
    <p>The following instructions were supplied by Slobodan Mumovic who
    says the one of the problems was the default JDBC connection pool
    configuration does not work with MSSQL.  For the following to be
    effective, you must have the MS SQL JDBC driver available.</p>
    
    
    <p>
    1 - set property: scarab.database.type=mssql in build.properties
    </p>
    <p>
    2. Edit the /src/conf/CustomSettings.properties file adding the following lines::
    </p>       
    
<pre>            
    torque.dsfactory.scarab.factory=org.apache.torque.dsfactory.TorqueDataSourceFactory
    torque.dsfactory.scarab.pool.defaultMaxConnections=10
    torque.dsfactory.scarab.pool.maxExpiryTime=3600
    torque.dsfactory.scarab.pool.connectionWaitTimeout=10
</pre>    
<p>
    3. Build the project using ant
</p>    
<p>
    4. Manually create the database in MSSQL Server with the user specified in
    step 1. as the DBO
</p>    
<p>    
    5. Execute the ant create-db target
 </p>    
<p>   
    6. Start scarab.
 </p>    
<p>   
    A later email states Scarab is still not usable on MSSQL:
</p>    
    <p>
    ... So we never actually used Scarab on MSSQL due to the following problems:
    </p>
    <p>
    1. Several tables are created with fields of type TEXT and IMAGE. This by
    itself would not be a problem but the code (I believe torque) uses "SELECT
    DISTINCT" on fields that contain TEXT and/or IMAGE. This could be fixed with
    a clever and insightful remapping of the JDBC to MSSQL data types in torque
    (/target/webapps/scarab/WEB-INF/src/torque/templates/sql/base/mssql/db.props
    ). But when I replaced IMAGE and TEXT with VARCHAR(xxxx) (where xxxx were
    several experimental values chosen not to overflow over the allowed limit
    for a data row) the result was that inserts of new issues simply hanged
    without any log or debug message of the reason. 
    
</p>    
<p>
    
    ... Here is what Eric Pugh discovered:
</p>    
<p>    
    After you run ant create-db, you need to 
    go into /target/scarab/web-inf/sql/mssql and edit the files:
</p>    
<p>    
    Must convert all BIGINT to int
    Convert TEXT to VARCHAR (2000).  Make sure to use whole word matching!
    Change OBJECT to something else, I think VARCHAR(2000).
</p>    
<p>    
    Then rerun ant create-db and the proper data types will be inserted!
</p>
  </section>
</body>
</document>