<usecase>
<number>05</number>
<title>Save Issue query</title>

<section>
<extends><a href="usecase03.html">UC-03</a>, <a href="usecase04.html">UC-04</a></extends>
<description>
       User performs query on the database. User is then given the
       option to save the query for use at a later date.
</description>
<features>None</features>
<players>
    <actor type="User">Any Role (High Priority, High Frequency)</actor>
    <actor type="Scarab">The scarab system</actor>
</players>
<stakeholders>
    <actor name="Project Participant">Wants to be able to search for an
    Issue with great detail (including all Attribute fields) and then be
    able to save it for reuse at a later date.
    </actor>
</stakeholders>
<prerequirements>
    <req>Logged in</req>
    <req>Project set up</req>
    <req>Existing Issue</req>
    <req>User knows some search terms</req>
</prerequirements>
<results>
<result>
After the search, a list of matching Issues are displayed or go directly
to the Issue if only one matches. A button and small text box is
presented on the results page that gives the user the chance to save the
query with a value that is typed in. If no value is typed in, then a
default value "Saved Query X" is assigned (where X is a number). After the
query has been saved, the query results page is displayed again.
</result>
<result>
There should also be a text entry box on the Issue Search page where the User
can type in the name for a saved query. This will save the query when the
search is done. The result is to show the search results page.
</result>
</results>
<datasets>
    <data>Query Terms</data>
    <data>Saved Query Name</data>
</datasets>
<faq>
<!--    <item q="">
    </item> -->    
</faq>
<notes>
    <note>Need to consider the ability to modify saved searches. This
    functionality should go into a search editor usecase.</note>
</notes>
<scenario>
      <ol>
        <li>User: click 'Search' link</li>
        <li>Scarab: display Search page</li>
        <li>User: Enter search criteria into field
            <ul type="a">
                <li>User: Enter name of saved query</li>
            </ul>
        </li>
        <li>User: hits 'search' button.</li>
        <li>[validation] Scarab: validates search criteria</li>
        <li>Scarab: searches for matching issues</li>
        <li>Scarab: filters search based on users role permissions.</li>
        <li>if results.size( ) == 0:
             <ul type="a">
               <li>Scarab: display message on ProjectIssues with field data as entered</li>
               <li>User: Modify search criteria and repeat</li>
             </ul>
        </li>
        <li>if results.size( ) == 1: 
             <ul type="a">
               <li>Scarab: display issue view page</li>
               <li>User: enter name of search to save. Clicks save button</li>
             </ul>
        </li>
        <li> if results.size( ) > 1:
             <ul type="a">
               <li>Scarab: display issue list page</li>
               <li>User: survey resulting list</li>
               <li>User: select one of the presented issues</li>
               <li>User: sort issues based on column heading</li>
               <li>User: modify displayed column headings</li>
               <li>User: enter name of search to save. Clicks save button</li>
             </ul>
        </li>
      </ol>
</scenario>
</section>
</usecase>
