<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

<properties>
    <title>How to Build Scarab</title>
    <author email="epugh@opensourceconnections.com">Eric Pugh</author>
</properties>

<body>


<section name=" Maven and/or Ant Build">
<subsection name="Generating Database">
<p>
	Now you can compile your code in either Ant or Maven.  However,	all of the database and torque OM related steps are 
	performed by the ant build.  You still generate your database by doing this:
	<source>
	cd build
	ant create-db
	</source>
	This will create in <code>/target/webapps/scarab/WEB-INF/sql</code> the various SQL files that you need.  It will also
	install the database for certain types of databases.  
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="Generating Torque Objects">
<p>
	Because the the various Torque objects are not checked into CVS, but instead are generated based on 
	your settings for the type of database, you still need to create the java files.
	<source>
	cd build
	ant
	</source>
	This will create in <code>/src/java</code> the various Torque objects.  You are now done with Ant and 
	you can continue the rest of the process in Maven or continue to use Ant.  You can now perform all the
	various functions of Maven that you would expect like running unit tests, producing WAR files, etc.
</p>
<p>
	<strong>Note:</strong> There is a Torque plugin for Maven that will do all of this.  The Ant steps
	will be removed once we have some more confort with Maven.  Also waiting for Maven 1.0 RC2 to be 
	released.
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Testing the code">
<p>
	To test that everything is working properly, you should run the unit tests!
	<source>
	cd /
	maven test
	</source>
	This will compile your newly generated Torque classes and run the unit tests.
	One thing to note is that in <code>/src/test/</code> are some config files that you probably will
	need to update the database settings for.
</p>
<p>
	If you want to see all the site documenation, then you can run
	<source>
	maven site
	</source>
	or, if you don't want to execute the unit tests (maybe they are failing)	
	<source>
	maven site -Dmaven.test.skip
	</source>
</p>
</subsection>

<subsection name="Creating a WAR file">
<p>
	Once things are to your liking you can use Maven to generate your WAR file:
	<source>
	maven war
	</source>
	This will compile Scarab, run the unit tests, and then generate in <code>/target</code> a
	WAR file that you can then use to deploy to any Servlet container.
</p>
<p>
	If you don't already have a configured Tomcat servlet container setup, then you
	can use the embedded Tomcat that comes with Scarab.  It is in the <code>/tomcat</code> directory.
	To set it up, you just need to put your WAR file in <code>/tomcat/webapps/</code>.  Take the existing
	<code>/tomcat/webapps/scarab.xml</code> file and rename it scarab.xml.off, as it is used for 
	inplace development.
	
</p>
</subsection>
</section>
<section name="In Place Development">
<subsection name="Intro">
<p>
	Scarab is setup to do inplace development.  This means that your webapp is set
	to be run from the <code>/src/webapp</code> directory.  This way you can change templates, edit
	config files and have the changes show up immediatly.  No need to do a build/deploy/run.
</p>
<p>
	Inplace development relies on the embedded Tomcat distribution at /tomcat.  The maven <code>scarab:inplace</code>
	goal will automatically setup the correct scarab Context file in /tomcat/webapps/. 
</p>
<p>
	If you are using an IDE like Eclipse, most changes like editing a .java file will 
	automatically restart Turbine for you.	
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="Eclipse Setup Directions">
<p>
	By default, Scarab is setup to use Eclipse as it's IDE.  To setup Scarab in Eclipse first run
	the eclipse plugin to generate the required files.
	<source>
	maven eclipse
	</source>
	Then you can open Eclipse and just import the Scarab directory.  The .classpath and .project files
	will be created for you so you are ready.  After the import you will need to do an Ant build to
	generate the Torque objects, to do this look at the section above labeled "Generating Torque Objects"
	(in the future Maven will be set-up to do this step, but for now you must use Ant).  Do a build in
	Eclipse to ensure everything compiles.
</p>		
<p>	
	You will then need to download	and install the 
	<a href="http://www.sysdeo.com/eclipse/tomcatPlugin.html">Sysdeo Tomcat</a> plugin.
</p>
<p>
	Restart Eclipse and then go to Window > Preferences and select the Tomcat option.  
</p>
<p>
	First select the Tomcat 4.1.x version of Tomcat, as that is what comes with Scarab.
</p>
<p>
	Set the tomcat home to:<code>C:\java\scarab\tomcat</code>, then the configuration file should 
	be set to: <code>C:\java\scarab\tomcat\conf\server.xml</code>.
</p>
<p>
	Next you do the Maven part.  There is a file called maven.xml that contains all the goals needed
	for setting up inplace development.  For other IDE's you may need to tweak this.
</p>
<p>
	From the root directory run the inplace setup goal.
	<source>
	maven scarab:inplace
	</source>
	This copies all the jars, classes, config files needed into your <code>/src/webapp/</code> directory, creating
	the <code>/src/webapp/WEB-INF/classes</code> and <code>/src/webapp/WEB-INF/conf</code> directories.  This
	will also rename your  <code>/tomcat/webapps/scarab.xml</code> to  <code>scarab.regular.xml.off</code>
	and take the special inplace file <code>scarab.inplace.xml.off</code> and rename it <code>scarab.xml</code>.	
</p>
<p>
	Now, right click your project in Eclipse and choose properties and then Tomcat.  Checkbox the 
	"Is Tomcat Project", set the context name to <code>scarab</code>, and UNCHECK the update server.xml.  Check the 
	mark as reloadable and redirect logging to Eclipse options.  Set the web application root to
	<code>/src/webapp</code>.  Save the changes and start up the Tomcat plugin.  Navigate in your browser to 
	<a href="http://localhost:8080/scarab">http://localhost:8080/scarab</a> and you should see the login page!
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="Eclipse Setup Directions">
<p>
Once you are done doing "in place" development, you can just run the goal to clean everything back up:
	<source>
	maven scarab:clean
	</source>
This will delete everything that was moved around by the inplace setup goal, as well as fix up your Scarab context
entries as well.  Now, when you run:	
	<source>
	maven war:webapp
	</source>
Everything will be put back!	
</p>
</subsection>
</section>

</body>
</document>
