<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document><properties><title>Scarab Design Document</title></properties><body><section name=""><p>In one sentence, <u>the goal of the Scarab project is to develop an easy to use 
    issue tracking system primarily using Java based technologies</u>. To break 
    this up, there are actually multiple goals to the Scarab project that can fall 
    under different categories. 
<ul>
    <li> Design and Architecture</li>
    <li> Database Schema</li>
    <li> Usability</li>
</ul>
<u><font color="#000000">Design and Architecture</font></u> <br></br>
Scarab is being designed from the ground up using Java based technology that has 
been developed explicitly for the purpose of developing web applications. This 
technology is called <a href="http://java.apache.org/turbine/">Turbine</a> and 
is available as an open source resource from Apache.org. Turbine has been developed 
over the course of the last couple of years by over 30 talented developers. Turbine 
provides the structure necessary to facilitate the development of web applications 
by combining not only a large collection of useful code, but a model in which 
to develop web applications. In addition to using Turbine, we will also be using 
<a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/velocity/">Velocity</a> as the template language 
for providing <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/turbine/turbine-2/pullmodel.html">Pull</a> 
MVC style development where the HTML is completely abstracted from the business 
logic of the application. We are aware that people often <i>claim </i>that their 
applications provide this, so we have worked hard to insure that this is a reality. 
</p><p>We choose Java based technologies for a few reasons. The first is that <a href="http://www.collab.net/">CollabNet</a> 
  developers are primarily interested in Java Servlets for developing web applications. 
  Servlets have many advantages over other technologies. They are fast, stable, 
  portable and easy to write. There are other languages such as Python and Perl 
  that are also popular and we hope that people will choose to use the Scarab 
  schema as the basis for developing their own front end applications. Just because 
  we have chosen Java does not mean that we are adverse to seeing Scarab implemented 
  in multiple different environments, it is just we needed to make a decision 
  and our first decision and priority is Java. :-) 
</p><p>We are not interested at this point in getting into language wars. We chose Java 
    and Java Servlets because they are a widely used technology that has been proven 
    to work in large scale systems. As stated above, we feel that designing a solid 
    schema foundation will allow anyone to port the UI front end of Scarab to any 
    other language. In fact, we are encouraging this. 
</p><p>Servlets by nature allow developers an easy way to create systems that can 
  run on multiple platforms. By default, Scarab will run equally and without code 
  changes on both Win32 and Unix systems. In fact, primary development is happening 
  on my Win32 box (and now my MacOS X box) using the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat/">Tomcat 
  4.0</a> servlet engine. Scarab will also run without modifications in any servlet 
  engine that implements JSDK 2.0 and higher although our target goal is to work 
  with Tomcat because it supports the newer API features such as WAR files. The 
  development database that will be used is MySQL. Scarab will be using the Object 
  Relational (OR) tool that is built into Turbine called <a href="http://java.apache.org/turbine/torque/">Torque</a>. 
  This tool will abstract out all the SQL by adding a layer on top of JDBC making 
  it possible to use any database without code changes. Schema's specific to Oracle 
  and MySQL will be distributed by default with Scarab. Schema contributions by 
  end users for other databases will also be included. In fact, Turbine's OR tool 
  has recently added support for a templated methodology for generating schema's 
  many of the major RDBM's (with the ability to easily add more). </p><p><u>Database Schema</u> <br></br>
  Our database schema has been developed in a platform neutral way so that it 
  will work on any SQL RDBMS. We are not taking advantage of any specific features 
  of the database. Instead, we are taking advantage of the OR tool that has been 
  developed within the Turbine framework. The Peer tool allows us to abstract 
  all of the specific database features into classes that are auto-generated. 
  The columns, rows and tables become objects that we can easily manipulate. The 
  benefit of doing things this way is that the schema is given room to grow and 
  change while still allowing the core application logic to be abstracted from 
  the database logic. People developing implementations of Scarab in other languages 
  only need to develop an IDBroker which is a <a href="http://www.ambysoft.com/mappingObjects.html">well 
  defined</a> methodology for providing efficient auto-increment functionality 
  that is outside of the database. 
</p><p>One goal of Scarab is to be able to translate from a <a href="http://www.bugzilla.org/docs/html/">Bugzilla</a> 
    schema to a Scarab schema. Given this requirement, the functionality within 
    the two schema's will remain consistent. For instance, a Milestone in Bugzilla 
    is still a Milestone in Scarab. The only primary differences between the two 
    will be additional features that are required by Scarab and a more thought out 
    and normalized database design. 
</p><p><u>Usability</u><br></br>
  We have spent quite a lot of time looking at other issue tracking systems and 
  we have tried to either copy or improve on top of those systems. A really good 
  example of one feature we are excited to add to Scarab (that helps illustrate 
  that we are thinking about this stuff) is a methodology that works like this: 
  The problem we are trying to cut down on is a fairly common problem: duplicate 
  issue reporting. Not only do we want to make it easy to mark an issue as a duplicate, 
  but how about doing something where the user starts to fill out an issue report 
  form and during the process an incremental search is performed for other issues 
  that match the one that you are filling in. That way, the user is presented 
  with a list of issues that potentially match their issue and are given the choice 
  to simply append on to an existing issue instead of creating a whole new one. 
</p><p>Page design and user interface is another factor of usability. Because we are 
    using Velocity and Turbine together, we are providing a way for people to easily 
    customize on a page by page basis the look and feel of Scarab without having 
    to dig into the actual Java code at all. The overall design is templated with 
    easy to modify layout and navigation modules. We have also enlisted the help 
    of UI design expert <a href="http://www.camworld.com/">Cameron Barrett</a> to 
    do a default design of both page flow through the system as well as look and 
    feel. <br></br>
    <br></br>
</p></section><section name=""><p>Scarab's initial goal is to have equal feature functionality to <a href="http://www.bugzilla.org/docs/html/">Bugzilla</a>, 
  because Bugzilla is the most used issue tracking system for OSS projects. While 
  Bugzilla is a great step forward from other systems (like GNATS), it is still 
  missing out on a good UI design, code design and database schema design. So, 
  what we have done is start with the concepts in Bugzilla's database schema and 
  identified areas where it can be improved through better design and additional 
  database normalization. Since we are using a web application framework (Turbine) 
  and back end technology (Java vs. Perl), we will also kill the code and design 
  problems inherent in Bugzilla with one stone. 
</p><p>A major problem with Bugzilla is that it is implemented in such a fashion that 
    security is not taken into consideration and this has resulted in being a catalyst 
    for high profiles sites being hacked into (including apache.org). The fact of 
    the matter is that Bugzilla was never meant to be used outside of Netscape and 
    the code shows. When Mozilla.org was created, there was a great hurry to provide 
    some sort of issue tracking system for people to use. Bugzilla was available 
    internally at Netscape and there were people at Netscape that knew how to install 
    and use it. To Mozilla.org's credit (and the contributors to the project), Bugzilla 
    has grown quite a bit, the TCL/TK dependencies were removed, the code has been 
    cleaned up quite a bit, bugs have been fixed and features added. The problem 
    is that this has been done on top of a poorly designed base which is not only 
    hard to setup and configure (the first thing you have to do is change the path 
    to the Perl executable in each and every file!), but also hard to customize 
    the look and feel of because much of the look and feel is hard coded in Perl 
    code. It is time to start over with something new that is designed from the 
    ground up to scale to other people's needs. 
</p><p><u>Processes</u> <br></br>
  There are some well defined process's within Bugzilla that we do appreciate. 
  For example, the <a href="http://www.mozilla.org/bugs/">Anatomy 
  of a Bugs Life</a> is a terrific example of how the whole process of dealing 
  with an issue should work. Duplicating these rules within Scarab is a priority 
  as doing it any other way would be simply reinventing the wheel. The point we 
  are trying to convey is that we are encouraging the idea of taking the good 
  pieces and dropping the bad. Another place that we will copy Bugzilla is in 
  their DTD definition. By using the same DTD as Bugzilla, we can more easily 
  implement import/export between Scarab and Bugzilla.<br></br>
    <br></br>
</p></section><section name=""><p>Here is a list of requirements that need to be accomplished by Scarab (at least 
    in the first round):</p><ul>
    <li>submit a new bug (both long form and single page)</li>
    <li> query and modify existing bugs</li>
    <li>manage patches and attachments</li>
    <li>users and roles</li>
    <li>create and remember reports that display metrics</li>
    <li>full web based administration of all aspects of the system</li>
    <li>ability to handle virtual hosting</li>
</ul></section><section name=""><p>Scarab is available at any point in time from <a href="/source/browse/scarab/">CVS</a>. 
  In the CVS tree (and the distribution), there is a top level document titled 
  <i>README.txt</i> that explains how to get up and running with Scarab. There 
  is also another documented titled DEVELOPMENT.txt that explains various things 
  that one should watch out for when developing Scarab.
</p><p>The layout of the top level directory structure in CVS looks something like 
  this:<br></br>
    
<table border="" cols="2" width="51%" height="125">
  <tr> 
    <td width="28%"><b>Directory</b></td>
    <td width="72%"><b>Description</b></td>
  </tr>
  <tr> 
    <td width="28%">build</td>
    <td width="72%">This is where the Ant build system lives</td>
  </tr>
  <tr> 
    <td width="28%">lib</td>
    <td width="72%">.jar libraries</td>
  </tr>
  <tr> 
    <td width="28%">src</td>
    <td width="72%"> 
      <p>All source code</p>
    </td>
  </tr>
  <tr> 
    <td width="28%">target</td>
    <td width="72%">When present, this contains the working build</td>
  </tr>
  <tr> 
    <td width="28%">www</td>
    <td width="72%">The scarab.tigris.org website and documentation</td>
  </tr>
</table>
</p><p>Within the <i>src/</i> directory, the structure looks like this:</p><table width="38%" border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="5" bgcolor="#CCCCCC">
    <tr> 
        
    <td>
      <pre>src/
            conf
            dtd
            html
            i18n
            images
            java/
                org/
                    tigris/
                        scarab/
                            actions/
                            attribute/
                            om/
                            pages/
                            screens/
                            services/
                            tools/
                            util/
            resources
            sql
            templates
                email/
                layouts/
                macros/
                navigations/
                pages/
                screens/                
            test
            tomcat-4.0
            usecases</pre>
        </td>
    </tr>
</table><p>The <i>java/</i> subdirectory contains all of the Java source code. Within 
  that directory is a package structure that is dictated by Java Coding Standards. 
  The coding standards that will be used by Scarab are the same as what is used 
  in the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/turbine/common/code-standards.html">Turbine 
  Project</a>. The Turbine layout standards which break up the content into various 
  modules such as Screen, Action and Page which are reflected by appropriate directories. 
  The om/ directory is where the Object Model code for 
  Scarab lives. This is the Java code that is mostly auto-generated that performs 
  the database abstraction. The <i>tools/</i> directory is where the Pull based 
  code will reside. This will be the API for Scarab. The <i>util/</i> directory 
  is for any utility code that is necessary for Scarab.</p><p>The <i>templates/</i> directory is where all the Velocity templates will live. 
    The directory structure is similar to what is in the java directory structure 
    which mirrors the Turbine module layout.</p><p>The <i>sql/</i> directory contains definition of database schema.</p><p>The <i>test/</i> directory contains the Java source code files related to
   unit testing for the application (we use JUnit).</p><p>The <i>html/</i> directory contains static web files belonging to project's web 
    application structure. The CSS also lives here as well.</p><p>The <i>images/</i> directory contains static images belonging to project's web 
    application structure.</p><p>The <i>conf/</i> directory contains configuration files for application server 
    and other tools that are running project's web application.</p><p>The <i>dtd/</i> directory contains the Scarab DTD and various other files
    surrounding the XML import/export functionality.</p><p>The <i>tomcat-X.X/</i> directory contains an appropriate version of
   <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat/">Tomcat</a> application
   server that is used to run project's web application.</p></section><section name=""><p>Scarab is being designed to be an <u>Issue Tracking System</u>. The primary goal 
    of Scarab is to duplicate Bugzilla functionality, therefore the immediate need 
    is to be able to track a single type of issue: bugs. Regardless of the current 
    requirements, we need to be able to handle our long term needs and thus the 
    schema and overall system design will reflect that need.</p><p><u>Projects/Components</u><br></br>
    Scarab has the concept of "<b>projects</b>". A project is a container 
    for separating code bases into groups. Within each project is one or more "<b>components</b>". 
    A component is a sub-project within the primary project. For example, <a href="http://argouml.tigris.org/v07/docs/codeorg.html">ArgoUML</a> 
    is a UML modeling tool. It would have a project titled "ArgoUML". 
    Within that project there are several components such as "GEF", "Documentation", 
    "UML meta-model", "user model", "design history", 
    etc. The purpose of splitting things up like this is to allow developers to 
    "subscribe" to projects and components that they are most interested 
    in while still allowing the system enough flexibility to support multiple uses. 
    In other words, it also allows people to use Scarab to host a multitude of projects 
    under a single Scarab installation.</p><p>Within each project, there will be the need to assign an owner of the project. 
    <u>The business logic is that when someone creates a new project, they become 
    the owner of that project</u>. An existing owner can always modify their role 
    within the project. However, they can only associate their ownership to another 
    user in the system. In other words, they cannot be removed from the administrative 
    function unless the Scarab system admin removes it. This is to prevent abuse. 
    The owner of the project has complete control over all aspects of that project 
    and the administrative interfaces will need to provide methods for modifying 
    a projects attributes. </p><p><u>Users/Visitors/Members</u><br></br>
  Each of these may be used all over the system to mean the same thing. What they 
  mean is a user who has registered with the installation of Scarab. Scarab stores 
  all of the user information in Turbine's TURBINE_USER table. In the future, 
  Scarab may opt to create its own Visitor table with Scarab specific columns 
  or simply create join tables that relate extra information to a user. In order 
  to perform any permanent tasks within Scarab such as creating a new issue, users 
  will be required to create an account. Users who have not logged into the system 
  are still tracked with their own unique session information, but it is lost 
  when it times out due to inactivity. The account can have any login name and 
  password. The only fields that will be required are first name, last name and 
  email address. </p><p>Email plays a crucial role in Scarab and having correct email addresses for users 
    is also crucial. There will be a default mechanism for validation of the email 
    address. The way that it works is that once the account is created, the user 
    will receive an email that will have a URL and a special key code in it. The 
    user can then click on the link and enter the special key code into the webpage. 
    This will confirm that the email address is valid and the user will then have 
    full access to the system. If the user attempts to log into the system before 
    they have confirmed their account, they will get the confirm account screen 
    before being allowed to continue. An example of this type of system is the way 
    that <a href="http://www.ebay.com/">Ebay.com</a> registration works.</p><p><u>Roles and Permissions</u><br></br>
    There will be several different types of users within the system. There is an 
    overall "<b>system admin</b>" who has root privileges over all the 
    administrative functions of the entire system. There will be a "<b>project 
    admin</b>" who has control over the projects that they are in charge of. 
    There will be a "<b>component admin</b>" who has control over a specific 
    component within the system. Each of these roles will have access only to the 
    specific areas of the website that their roles allow. For example, a "component 
    admin" will not be able to modify a project's details, but they will be 
    able to modify a component's details. The most common user will be "<b>mortal</b>" 
    user who can only submit and query for issues. Whether or not the "mortals" 
    can post across projects and components is still up for debate and will probably 
    be a configuration option within Scarab. Currently, Bugzilla does not have that 
    level of control.</p><p>Areas of the website that a particular user does not have access to should 
  not be shown and the links to go to those areas should not be displayed. If 
  the user attempts to access one of these areas by entering a URL, the system 
  will redirect them to a login page. The UI design will need to account for the 
  fact that data may or may not exist depending on which user is logged into the 
  system.</p><p>The implementation of the access control will be inherited from Turbine's <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/turbine/turbine-3/apidocs/org/apache/turbine/modules/actions/AccessController.html">ACL 
  System</a>. The idea being that a user can have one or more roles. Roles are 
  a collection of one or more permissions. Thus, you can either validate access 
  based on their role or their permission. We will also probably have to extend 
  the functionality of Turbine's system to also include Project specific permissions. 
  The details of the implementation of this still need further consideration. 
  For the initial round of Scarab development, the system will error on being 
  less secure with the idea of needing more security further down the road. The 
  idea being that it is easier to lock down something that already exists than 
  to plan for it in advance because it is very difficult to predict the level 
  of control that the application needs beyond the user roles mentioned above. 
</p><p><u>Virtual Hosting Domains</u><br></br>
    There is a requirement to allow Scarab to work with a single installation across 
    multiple domains hosted on a single server. In other words, if a user logs into 
    scarab.tigris.org, then that user should be presented with bugs that relate 
    only to scarab.tigris.org. Searches and queries should occur either across multiple 
    domains and projects or within the individual project. This should be controlled 
    as a preference setting within the individual domain. Installations that only 
    have a single domain would be treated as such. The information for these domains 
    is reflected in the Schema. The following schemes need to be supported: http://project.domain/, 
    http://domain/project and http://project.domain/project/.</p><p><u>Email</u><br></br>
    The role of email within Scarab will be mostly from a sending vs. receiving 
    standpoint. There are other bug tracking systems such as GNATS that give users 
    the ability to send either specially formatted emails or have emails appended 
    to an existing issue. The problem with this is that it is very difficult to 
    get users to format their emails appropriately and it is even more difficult 
    to write a parser to deal with badly formatted emails. In the end, the whole 
    issue becomes increasingly sticky, for example, what do you do with a badly 
    formatted email? Send it back to the user and ask them to resubmit it? While 
    Unix hackers are willing to accept such abuse, the fact of the matter is that 
    regular users are not.</p><p>Instead, Scarab is going to circumvent the entire email submission process 
  by simply not <u>initially</u> allowing it. The future plans will be to accept 
  an XML formatted piece of data. This will be implemented with <a href="http://xml.apache.org/soap/">SOAP</a> 
  (or something like it) technology. By using XML, it will be easy to provide 
  the user with a template that they can fill out. It will also be easy to use 
  an existing XML parser such as <a href="http://xml.apache.org/xerces-j/">Xerces</a> 
  to parse the data and perform actions on it including validation. We will <a href="http://scarab.tigris.org/servlets/ReadMsg?list=dev&amp;msgNo=144">take 
  advantage of Bugzilla's DTD</a> for defining a bug.</p><p>On the other side, sending email will be a very large part of Scarab. Nearly 
  every "event", such as a modification to an issue will be broadcast 
  to all of the necessary people or (if configured) mailing lists. The emails 
  themselves will be Velocity template files that get processed in order to insert 
  dynamic data. The benefit of this is that the end users of Scarab will be able 
  to customize the default emails as easily as they can customize the look and 
  feel of the website. The emails will contain as many links as necessary that 
  the user can click on to allow actions to be performed. For example, if the 
  user is required to approve something, the user will get an email that states 
  what needs to be approved and provides a single URL to click on that will take 
  them to the website, allow them to log in and then provide a page that will 
  allow them to execute the approval by clicking a single button. The link could 
  also be coded to simply perform the action after login, but we want to provide 
  a way to pre-confirm things before execution in order to provide a level of 
  control over what happens. The emails will also contain helpful information 
  about the processes. For example, if a Milestone has been reached, give direction 
  on what to do next and guide the user as much as possible.</p><p>Email will also be used to "bug" developers that they need to perform 
    some action by a certain date and time. For example, any bug that you have assigned 
    to you that is older than some defined amount of time will cause an email to 
    be sent to you that reminds you that you need to be working on this particular 
    bug. It will be possible to log into the system and put the bug into a "sleep" 
    mode for the next period of time.</p><p><u>Attachments/Patches</u><br></br>
    Attachments can be associated with an individual issue. An attachment can take 
    the form of a simple text diff patch or an entire binary file. The user interface 
    needs to be designed to allow people to choose the type of attachment they are 
    making and deal with it appropriately. The system will need to have a methodology 
    for managing each of the patches. The data from the uploaded information will 
    be stored in the database by default although the table will contain a column 
    that allows patches to be located as a URL resource as well.</p><p><u>Attributes</u><br></br>
    Attributes are things like <b>Milestone</b>, <b>Priority</b>, <b>Status</b>, 
    <b>Resolution</b> and <b>Severity</b>. The functionality of these as well as 
    the definition is being initially <a href="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/bugzilla/documentation.html">duplicated</a> 
    from Bugzilla. The reason is that it not only a good common design, but it also 
    makes a Bugzilla-&gt;Scarab database conversion tool easier to create. The difference 
    between Bugzilla and Scarab in this respect is in the database design. We have 
    identified the fact that nearly all of these attributes are the same thing. 
    Thus, we have provided a normalized schema that accounts for that as well as 
    for the fact that there may be localization issues. For example, we are building 
    in the ability to give each project control over what the definitions are for 
    each of the attributes as well as providing definitions that can be displayed 
    in a particular language depending on which language you have set in your browser. 
    The management of all of the attributes will be through a web based interface. 
    There will be a default set of values for the attributes that are defined in 
    a properties file. Then, each project and component within the system will have 
    the ability to override these defaults and define their own.</p><p>The definition of what should happen when a project reaches a particular milestone 
    still needs to be defined. Certainly, email will be sent. :-) There should be 
    some sort of definition of what sequence of events is enforced and how. Someone 
    should not be able to skip milestones unless they have the permission to do 
    so. The reason this has yet to be defined is because we do not have a working 
    system yet to help us define what is best for the users. This is something that 
    comes during user testing.</p><p><u>Voting</u><br></br>
    Scarab will have a feature that will allow users to vote on which issues are 
    important to them. This should also help project developers to prioritize which 
    bugs are fixed first. There will be screens which display reports based on the 
    votes.</p><p><u>Dependencies</u><br></br>
    Bugs can depend on one or more other bugs. These can be tracked within Scarab 
    (for example another issue id) or as a URL to another resource. A single issue 
    can have dependencies on more than one issue. It should be possible to display 
    a page that shows the tree or graph of the dependencies. The definition of what 
    should happen regarding dependencies still needs to be discussed. For example, 
    what should happen if one bug depends on another bug and it is closed? A lot 
    of this is <a href="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/bugzilla/documentation.html">already 
    covered</a> in Bugzilla, but it should be eventually restated here for clarification.</p><p><u>Change Tracking</u><br></br>
    All changes that occur will be tracked. The user who made the change, the time 
    they made the change, etc. This will allow people to view the history of the 
    issue quickly and easily. We should consider providing some sort of graphical 
    view of the changes through creative use of HTML and/or dynamic image generation.</p><p><u>Enhancement/Wishlist Tracking/TODO/Tasks</u><br></br>
    Part of the UI should have a specific feature for tracking enhancement requests 
    specifically. An enhancement is essentially a issue of type enhancement, but 
    for UI purposes, it would be nice to have a link where someone could click on 
    it and a list of the enhancement requests are displayed. The actual implementation 
    of this UI will be left up to Cameron to decide on what is best.</p><p><u>Support Tracking</u><br></br>
    This is similar to the above tracking in that it is essentially another type 
    of issue, but it is listed here seperately because the user interface should 
    allow a user to enter a support issue which would allow the developers to track 
    a conversation with a user. It might work something like this:</p><p>Imagine a FAQ/support tracking tool with a feature where 
    someone asks a question and it bugs a developer via email until that person 
    either answers the question or assigns the issue to someone else. If the person 
    answers the question, then it will automatically become part of the larger FAQ 
    system. I think that would be a very cool feature, but is essentially beyond 
    the scope of Scarab for Alpha 1.</p><p><u>Integration with Source Version Control (<a href="http://subversion.tigris.org/">Subversion</a>)</u><br></br>
  To be discussed further. Essentially, the idea is that <a href="http://subversion.tigris.org/">Subversion</a> 
  can be provided API's to allow it to send events to Scarab (for example, through 
  <a href="http://xml.apache.org/soap/">SOAP</a>). Scarab can also use the client 
  libraries to communicate directly with Subversion. Since neither project is 
  finished yet, we can only try to consider ideas on how they will be integrated 
  together. One blue sky feature would be to do something like <a href="http://scarab.tigris.org/servlets/ReadMsg?list=dev&amp;msgNo=149">this</a>.
  Further input here is appreciated.</p></section><section name=""><p><u>Initial Experience</u><br></br>
    When the user first accesses the system, they will be presented with a screen 
    that welcomes them to the system and provides a search interface for finding 
    projects as well as logging in. If the user logs in, then they are presented 
    with their own personalized homepage that remembers various settings such as 
    the projects the user is associated with as well as frequent queries, bugs they 
    want to track, and vote counts. There will need to be a "preferences" 
    area of the site that allows the user to customize what is displayed on this 
    page. The idea is to make it as painless as possible to allow the user to use 
    the system.</p><p>When the user selects a project, they will then be able to start a wizard like 
    process of entering their bug. They can also circumvent that process and fill 
    out a single page report, but this loses the nice process that has been described 
    above regarding duplicate issue handling.</p><p>Users should also be able to browse the projects in the system as well as the 
    bugs within the project in an ordered fashion. Users should also be able to 
    go directly to a particular bug and view its status quickly and easily.</p><p>One complaint about Bugzilla is that the page that is used to fill out a bug 
    is the same page that is used to display the bug, even if the user does not 
    have access to modify the bugs contents. This has an unfortunate side effect 
    of teasing a user into thinking they can modify the contents of the bug, so 
    they spend time changing things only to find out after the fact that they can't 
    modify the bug. We would like to solve this UI issue by simply making fields 
    that cannot be edited static and not displayed as a HTML form.</p><p>Instead of requiring users to bookmark pages, we should provide an interface 
    that accomplishes the same goals. Users should be able to bookmark their queries 
    and which issues matter to them. The should be able to access this information 
    from their customized homepage. If a user does decide to bookmark a page, the 
    system should know how to display that page given that the bookmark is fairl 
    valid. Not all pages will be able to be bookmarked without following a link 
    that specificially allows them to bookmark the page. An example of this is on 
    news sites that have a link to allow the user bookmark the page.</p><p><u>Reports/Metrics</u><br></br>
    It should be possible to easily create reports that track the life cycle of 
    issues within a project. The granularity will be split up at the component level. 
    For example, it will be possible to determine the number of outstanding issues 
    within a project and within that projects specific components. Dependency and 
    Vote reports should also be created. It should also be possible to create metrics 
    across projects such as which project has had the most bugs fixed.</p><p><u>Administration</u><br></br>
    Links to the administration portion of the website will only be shown when the 
    user has been logged into the system AND they have enough privileges to access 
    that resource. The admin area will need to have the ability to modify all aspects 
    of the database and system easily. There will also need to be various levels 
    of admin interaction depending on which role the user has. The implementation 
    of this will probably be better handled through the use of multiple screens 
    and actions that are specific to the purpose versus trying to hide and show 
    content and actions depending on user roles because of security reasons. The 
    side effect to this may be the duplication of some screen and action code. An 
    interface to manage the virtual domains and their preferences should be created. 
</p><p><u>Help System</u><br></br>
    Scarab will have a contextual help system that explains different areas of the 
    system in detail. The idea is that you will be able to click on a link and a 
    small new window will pop-up that displays information pertaining to the process. 
    One design goal for the system is that a help system should really not be needed. 
    It is provided more as a convenience factor. The user should not have to guess 
    at what to do next, the path should be predetermined and clear.</p></section></body></document>