<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Changes</title>
    <author email="epugh@opensourceconnections.com">Eric Pugh</author>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <release version="b20" date="in dev">
    </release>

    <release version="b19" date="13-Apr-2004">
      <action dev="legout" type="update">
        SCB1120 - Most of the text entry input boxes now fill the
        width of the page, resizing with the browser window.
      </action>
      <action dev="hdabbous" type="fix">
        Registration Email is generated with the correct
        characterset from the configuration.
      </action>
      <action dev="hdabbous" type="add">
        The default characterset has been changed from
        dynamic to UTF-8. This is necessary, when the
        ResourceBundle resolver mixes resources from
        different Locales (e.g. korean and english).
      </action>
      <action dev="hdabbous" type="add">
        Scarab now searches the ResourceBundles
        following all browser specified Locales in
        user prefered order. Ensure, that Scarab resolves
        unresolved references from the english ResourceBundle.
      </action>
      <action dev="pledbrook" type="fix">
        SCB1131 - No longer get an error on the "possible duplicates found"
        screen on systems lacking the sample data.
      </action>
      <action dev="pledbrook" type="fix">
         SCB670 - Query results screen now honours the number of results
         per page, the sort column and the sort polarity from a saved
         query.
      </action>
      <action dev="pledbrook" type="fix">
        SCB544 - Dates can now be entered into the advanced query screen in the
        user's locale, rather than in the US date format.
      </action>
      <action dev="pledbrook" type="fix">
        SCB1065 - the admin user can now change their own details, although they
        can no longer change users' passwords.
      </action>
      <action dev="epugh" type="add">
        Integrated Peter's scarab properties xml file to generate as part of the site docs.
      </action>
      <action dev="hdabbous" type="fix">
        Localised most (if not all) of the remaining unlocalised messages,
        excluding exceptions.
      </action>
      <action dev="epugh" type="fix">
        Updated Scarab to use the latest Turbine 3.  Turbine 3 (and T2.3) use a log4j.properties file for
        configuring logging.  Fixes the logs not showing up problem.
      </action>       
      <action dev="epugh" type="update">
        Removed references to Turbine Scheduler that wasn't used.
      </action>      
      <action dev="hdabbous" type="add">
        If you are using Ant1.6, you get a nice error message.  Need to use Ant 1.5.4 right now.
      </action>    
      <action dev="pledbrook" type="update">
        Renamed the locale resource bundles to minimise duplicates and to
        follow a more standard form.
      </action>
      <action dev="epugh" type="add">
        Revamped the site docs to be in xdoc format.  Integrated the existing docbook formatted admin guides.
        Added a tasks.xml file to track the roadmap to 1.0.
      </action>             
      <action dev="hdabbous" type="add">
        <a href="http://scarab.collab.net/scarab/issues/id/SCB1030">SCB1030</a> 
        Added a valve that updates the database with the user's preferred
        locale if it changes. The check is done each request, and the
        locale is used to generate e-mails in the correct language.
      </action>
    <action dev="epugh" type="add">
        Add goal scarab:sample that leverages NSIS to create an installer for windows that bundles a Scarab, 
        Hypersonic, and Tomcat.  This is already to install and run!
      </action>    
    <action dev="epugh" type="add">
        First cut at using Hypersonic as the embedded database.  The database must manually be started via
        a batch file, but then can be used for running unit tests or sampling the webapp.
      </action>         
    <action dev="epugh" type="add">
        Generate into the WEB-INF/sql/ directory all the SQL DDL scripts for all the databases 
        supported by Scarab.
      </action>      
    <action dev="epugh" type="add">
        ConfigurationFactory is now used!  Provides ability to define at runtime which sources of
        Configuration data to check.  You can now override ANY property set in TR.props.
      </action>         
    <action dev="pledbrook" type="fix">
        SCB1072 getRModuleAttributes() and getRIssueTypeAttributes()
        have been modified to return empty lists, rather than
    null, if no attributes exist in the group.
      </action>       
    <action dev="epugh" type="update">
        Reorganized all the webapp assets under /src/webapp.  Allows easy inplace development.
        Additionally, you can now use either Ant or Maven!
      </action>        
      <action dev="vprus" type="add">
        <a href="http://scarab.collab.net/scarab/issues/id/SCB132">SCB132</a>, 
        <a href="http://scarab.collab.net/scarab/issues/id/SCB613">SCB613</a>
        Email notification on Role Requests
      </action>           
      <action dev="hdabbous" type="add">
        <a href="http://scarab.collab.net/scarab/issues/id/SCB1026">SCB1026</a> 
        l10n fixes, and patches to German language bundle.
      </action>
      <action dev="epugh" type="add">
        Added Maven generated docs to scarab-gen.
      </action>             
    </release>
    <release version="b18-1" date="27-Jan-2004">
      <action dev="pledbrook" type="fix">
        Fixed the line-endings on all *.sh and *.bat files.
      </action>
      <action dev="vprus" type="fix">
        Refactoring of Email.java.
      </action>             
    </release>
    <release version="b18" date="6-Jan-2004">
      <action dev="" type="fix">
        SCB327  Datadump does not handle nulls properly
      </action>             
      <action dev="" type="fix">
        SCB627   Most recent  query returns incomplete results
      </action>
      <action dev="" type="fix">
        SCB799  "commit" warnings with PostgreSQL"
      </action>
      <action dev="" type="fix">
        SCB888  Multi-line long-string attributes do not display correctly
      </action>
      <action dev="" type="add">
        SCB898   modify src sql scarab schema xml to support DB2
      </action>
      <action dev="" type="add">
        SCB899   modify src sql scarab sample data sql to support
      </action>
      <action dev="" type="add">
        Remove unneeded setDistinct from QueryPeer.jav
      </action>
      <action dev="" type="fix">
        SCB930   ResourceNotFoundException when saving query if All Issues Types is selected
      </action>
      <action dev="" type="fix">
        SCB941   Update language bundles for b16
      </action>   
      <action dev="" type="fix">
        SCB952   Add remove attributes from view  does not work properly
      </action>   
      <action dev="" type="fix">
        SCB953  Comments with more than 255 characters
      </action>   
      <action dev="" type="fix">
        SCB957  Attribute changes missing in the History
      </action>   
      <action dev="" type="fix">
        SCB958   defect in scarab when creating a new enhancement issue
      </action>   
      <action dev="" type="fix">
        SCB964  Session lost on multiple pages
      </action>   
      <action dev="" type="fix">
        SCB965  duplicate check remove special chars
      </action>                                                                                            
      <action dev="" type="fix">
        SCB970  check.Scarab.properties
      </action> 
      <action dev="" type="fix">
        SCB972  When adding personnel to an issue, next and previous links don't work
      </action> 
      <action dev="" type="fix">
        SCB978   Issue Types Headers Displayed When No Issue Types Present  
      </action> 
      <action dev="" type="fix">
        SCB984  Locale en_NZ not supported
      </action> 
      <action dev="" type="fix">
        SCB986  incorrect query results with hierarchy
      </action> 
      <action dev="" type="fix">
        SCB997  Non-expiring password setting in scarab.props causes NumberFormatException
      </action> 
      <action dev="" type="fix">
        SCB1008 role approval deny failure in localized message.
      </action>                                     
      <action dev="" type="fix">
        SCB1011 postgresql referential integrity violation during sample data insert
      </action>  
      <action dev="" type="fix">
        SCB1014  Adding a new issue type to a module causes exception
      </action>  
      <action dev="" type="add">
        SCB1028 PostgreSQL v7.4 and Scarab
      </action>              
    </release>    
  </body>
</document>

